<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: emacs | adereth]]></title>
  <link href="http://adereth.github.io/blog/categories/emacs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://adereth.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-20T17:28:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://adereth.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Adereth]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Most frequently enabled Emacs packages]]></title>
    <link href="http://adereth.github.io/blog/2013/12/08/most-frequently-enabled-emacs-packages/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-08T20:38:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://adereth.github.io/blog/2013/12/08/most-frequently-enabled-emacs-packages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the Emacs-24.4 release, emacs-devel is conducting <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/FrequentlyEnabledPackages_Emacs244_Survey">a survey</a> to find out which vanilla GnuEmacs packages/modes people enable by default.  The responses are in one big plain-text alphabetical list which isn&rsquo;t really conducive to browsing.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve gone through the most frequently enabled ones to see what they do.  I figured others might be interested, so I&rsquo;ve put the top ones in order of popularity, along with brief descriptions and links to the related pages if one exists.  Enjoy!</p>

<ul>
<li><p><code>uniquify</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/uniquify">Uniquify</a> overrides the default mechanism for making buffer names unique (using suffixes like <code>&lt;2&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;3&gt;</code> etc.) with a more sensible behaviour which use parts of the file names to make the buffer names distinguishable.  This will be turned on by default in 24.4.</p></li>
<li><p><code>column-number-mode</code> &ndash; Displays which column the cursor is currently on in the mode line.</p></li>
<li><p><code>show-paren-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/ShowParenMode">show-paren-mode</a> allows you to see matching pairs of parentheses and other characters. When the cursor is on one of the paired characters, the other is highlighted.</p></li>
<li><p><code>ido-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/InteractivelyDoThings">Ido</a> lets you interactively do things with buffers and files.  The <a href="http://www.masteringemacs.org/articles/2010/10/10/introduction-to-ido-mode/">Introduction to Ido Mode</a> on <a href="http://www.masteringemacs.org/">Mastering Emacs</a> does a much better job of explaining why and how you should use it.</p></li>
<li><p><code>transient-mark-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/TransientMarkMode">Transient Mark mode</a> gives you much of the standard selection-highlighting behavior of other editors.  This is on by default in recent Emacsen.</p></li>
<li><p><code>ibuffer</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/IbufferMode">Ibuffer</a> is an advanced replacement for BufferMenu, which lets you operate on buffers much in the same manner as Dired.</p></li>
<li><p><code>blink-cursor-mode</code> &ndash; Toggle cursor blinking.  This is on by default.</p></li>
<li><p><code>flyspell-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/FlySpell">Flyspell</a> enables on-the-fly spell checking in Emacs by the means of a minor mode.</p></li>
<li><p><code>recentf-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/RecentFiles">Recentf</a> is a minor mode that builds a list of recently opened files. This list is is automatically saved across Emacs sessions. You can then access this list through a menu.</p></li>
<li><p><code>eldoc-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/ElDoc">Eldoc-mode</a> is a MinorMode which shows you, in the echo area, the argument list of the function call you are currently writing.</p></li>
<li><p><code>dired-x</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/DiredExtra">Dired X</a> provides extra functionality for DiredMode.</p></li>
<li><p><code>windmove</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/WindMove">Wind Move</a> lets you move point from window to window using Shift and the arrow keys.</p></li>
<li><p><code>line-number-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/LineNumbers">Line Numbers</a> displays line numbers in a buffer, or otherwise indicates line numbers, without actually changing the buffer content.</p></li>
<li><p><code>winner-mode</code> &ndash; <a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/WinnerMode">Winner Mode</a> allows you to undo and redo changes in the window configuration with the key commands <code>C-c left</code> and <code>C-c right</code>.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
